# JOEL DOUGLASS

Principle Web Developer · Boston, MA · joel@joeldouglass.com · (857) 998-0462

#### ABOUT ME

I'm a full stack developer with over 15 years of experience in software and web development. Lately, I've been into data—visualization, communication and management systems—as a *Principal Developer* at **Velir**, where I lead the Data Visualization practice area. On the tech side, I'm most experienced with Javascript (browser or Node.js) and .NET (C#, ASP), but I consider myself a polyglot and have dabbled in everything from C, C++ and Java to Clojure.

# **NOTABLE PROJECTS**

# Shift Workers by the Numbers - Purpose Campaigns

2018

Communicating large numbers is hard. This custom visualization attempts to effectively show the large number of U.S. citizens that are affected by a variable work schedule. *Lead Developer · WebGL, three.js, React.js ·* https://workshift.us/numbers

# Quality-Spending Interactive - Commonwealth Fund

2018

Healthcare performance varies widely across the U.S. In this custom visualization, health care quality is contrasted with spending by U.S. state. *Lead Developer · D3.js, AngularJS ·* http://tools.commonwealthfund.org/interactives-and-data/spending-vs-quality-interactive

## CMS Hospital Quality Chartbook - Centers for Medicare and Medicaid

2015-present

This collection of data visualizations aims to compare hospital quality statistics around the country. Management of data and content using Drupal. *Visualization Lead, Developer · Angular,js, D3,js, Drupal ·* https://cmshospitalchartbook.com

## Nationwide Adult Medicaid CAHPS - Centers for Medicare and Medicaid

2016-17

The NAM CAHPS survey is administered to capture baseline estimates of adult Medicaid enrollees' experiences with the health care system. This site was built from the ground up to communicate the results. Lead Back End Developer ASP.NET, SQL Server, React.js, D3.js · https://nam-cahps.medicaid.gov

## The Kauffman Index - Ewing Marion Kauffman Foundation

2016

A custom mini-site who's goal is to communicate entrepreneurship statistics around the country. This data exploration site was built into the Foundation's existing Sitecore implementation. Lead Developer · Node.js, PostgreSQL, Sitecore, React.js, D3.js · https://www.kauffman.org/kauffman-index

# **AARP Data Explorer** - Annie E. Casey Foundation

2015-16

Built for the AARP Public Policy Institute, this data exploration site allows on-demand publishing of new data and updates. *Tech Lead, Developer · ASP.NET, SQL Server, Angular.js, D3.js, Highcharts.js ·* https://dataexplorer.aarp.org

## What Would Happen if Health Care in your State Improved? - Commonwealth Fund

2014-17

This custom interactive lets visitors explore how health care performance might be different if their state performed as well (or as badly) as other states. Lead Developer  $\cdot$  D3.js, AngularJS  $\cdot$  http://tools.commonwealthfund.org/interactives-and-data/estimated-impact-interactive

# Kids Count Data Center - Annie E. Casey Foundation

2013-present

The Kids Count Data Center project is designed to communicate childhood wellbeing data. Built to support 50+ grantees around the U.S. uploading and publishing new data daily. Lead Developer · ASP.NET, SQL Server, Backbone.js, High-charts.js, Openlayers.js · https://datacenter.kidscount.org

## **Kidsdata.org** - Lucile Packard Foundation for Children's Health

2013-present

Similar to the Kids Count Datacenter, but narrowing in on detailed data in the state of California. Kidsdata.org includes a highly customized administration interface for publishing new data and content. *Lead Developer · ASP.NET, SQL Server, Backbone.js, Highcharts.js, Openlayers.js ·* https://www.kidsdata.org

#### EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

## Principal Developer, Data Visualization Practice Lead - Velir · Somerville, MA

2013-Present

- Consult on company strategy for data visualization and communication projects
- Evaluate and adopt emerging tools, languages, and frameworks
- · Design and document practice area workflows and processes
- Contribute estimates and technology/system proposals to business development teams
- · Lead both front and back end project teams by assigning tasks and tracking progress

## Senior Developer - Velir · Somerville, MA

2010-13

- · Led project development teams by assigning tasks and tracking progress
- Designed custom web applications built on the Sitecore CMS and other platforms
- Estimated new project and enhancement work

# Web Developer - Velir · Somerville, MA

2008-10

- Worked closely with lead developers to turn designs and requirements into functioning web applications.
- Contributed to new application builds on the Sitecore CMS
- Maintained legacy systems built on ColdFusion, Classic ASP and Perl

## Senior Systems Engineer - General Dynamics, C4 Systems · Needham, MA

2003-06

- Designed, developed, and executed a full test suite for custom Network Interface (NIC) hardware
- Held a U.S. DoD SECRET security clearance

#### **EDUCATION**

# B.S. Computer and Systems Engineering - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute · Troy, NY

1999-03

- Concetration in Control Systems
- · Graduated Summa Cum Laude



Fork on GitHub github.com/joeldouglass/resume